Guide to the Praeger Department of Parks survey and photographs V1974.003
Brooklyn Historical Society
Praeger Department of Parks survey and photographs
1934-1935
Brooklyn Historical Society
Praeger, Emil
V1974.003
3 Linear Feet in three record cartons.
The Praeger Department of Parks survey and photographs document every park, playground, and gore in New York City at the time of the study, as well as undeveloped land owned by the parks department. The survey and photographs show the parks of New York City on the eve of improvements and development funded by the Works Progress Administration.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Source and date of acquisition for this collection are unknown. This collection was accessioned in 1974.
Existence and Location of Copies
Item-level description and digital versions of Brooklyn images from the collection are available for searching via the image database in the library under the object ID prefix V1974.3.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by borough. Within each borough, the folders are arranged alphabetically by park name.
Historical note
In 1934, Mayor Fiorella LaGuardia united each of the five New York City borough parks departments under a new city-wide Department of Parks. That year, under the direction of commissioner Robert Moses, the department conducted a study titled "Comprehensive Survey of the Parks and Playgrounds in New York City," documenting all public spaces in the city overseen by the parks department. The study was conducted by Emil Praeger (1892-1973), chief engineer for the Department of Parks.
Sources:
"Emil Prager, 81, Engineer, Is Dead." New York Times, October 17, 1973, 44.
New York City Department of Parks and Recreation. "Online Historic Tour: Robert Moses and the Modern Park System (1929-1965)." Accessed May 11, 2011. http://www.nycgovparks.org/sub_about/parks_history/historic_tour/history_robert_moses_modern.html
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
The collection's digital surrogates should be used in place of the originals whenever possible.
Scope and Contents
The Praeger Department of Parks survey and photographs date from 1934-1935 and measure 3 linear feet. The Praeger survey, titled "Comprehensive Survey of the Parks and Playgrounds in New York City," documents every park, playground, and gore in New York City at the time of the study, as well as undeveloped land owned by the parks department. The survey and photographs show the parks of New York City on the eve of improvements and development funded by the Works Progress Administration.
For each property, the survey includes a description of the park with location, acreage, state of development, neighborhood population information, proposed improvements to the park, and future development possibilities. Accompanying each park survey is a ledger detailing material, equipment, and labor needs for proposed improvements, as well as an architectural drawing of the park and its features. Photographs provide visual documentation of the state of the parks, as well as major thoroughfares near parks. Each image in the collection is identified by park name, neighborhood, and cross streets.
The collection is arranged by borough, then alphabetically by park name. Photographs of Brooklyn parks are available in the library's image database. The collection covers parks in 36 Brooklyn neighborhoods with 231 images.
Parks -- New York (State) -- New York; Landscape photography -- New York (State) -- New York; Photographs; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Manhattan (New York, N.Y.); Staten Island (New York, N.Y.) -- Maps; Queens (New York, N.Y.); Bronx (New York, N.Y.); Land surveys; Playgrounds -- New York (State) -- New York; New York (N.Y.)
- Parks Department budget request memorandum, 1935 (Box 1)
- Schedule of Parks (Box 1)
- Architectural renderings (Box 1)
- Brooklyn
  - American Playground, V1974.3.1-2 (Box 1)
    Greenpoint (New York, N.Y.)
  - Amersford Park, V1974.3.3-4 (Box 1)
    Flatlands (New York, N.Y.)
  - Bartel-Pritchard Square, V1974.3.5 (Box 1)
    Park Slope (New York, N.Y.); Windsor Terrace (New York, N.Y.)
  - Bay Parkway, V1974.3.6 (Box 1)
  - Bay Ridge Parkway, V1974.3.7 (Box 1)
    Bay Ridge (New York, N.Y)
  - Betsy Head (Memorial) Playground, V1974.3.8 (Box 1)
    Brownsville (New York, N.Y.)
  - Beatty Square, V1974.3.9 (Box 1)
    Bushwick (New York, N.Y.); Williamsburg (New York, N.Y.); Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.)
  - Bensonhurst Park, V1974.3.10 (Box 1)
    Bensonhurst (New York, N.Y.)
  - Borough Hall Park, V1974.3.11 (Box 1)
    Downtown Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.)
  - Brooklyn Botanic Garden, V1974.3.12-13 (Box 1)
    Prospect Heights (New York, N.Y.); Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Prospect Lefferts Gardens (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
  - Brooklyn Heights Parks, V1974.3.14 (Box 1)
    Brooklyn Heights (New York, N.Y.)
  - Brower Park and additions, V1974.3.15-17 (Box 1)
    Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.)
  - Browne Park, V1974.3.18 (Box 1)
    Fort Greene (New York, N.Y.)
  - Buffalo Avenue Parkway, V1974.3.19 (Box 1)
  - Bushwick Parkway, V1974.3.20 (Box 1)
    Bushwick (New York, N.Y.)
  - Bushwick Park, V1974.3.21-24 (Box 1)
    Ridgewood (New York, N.Y.)
  - Bushwick Playground, V1974.3.25-28 (Box 1)
  - Canarsie Park, V1974.3.29-32 (Box 1)
    Canarsie (New York, N.Y.)
  - Carroll Park, V1974.3.33-34 (Box 1)
    Carroll Gardens (New York, N.Y.)
  - Cathedral Place, V1974.3.35 (Box 1)
  - City Park, V1974.3.36-37 (Box 1)
    Biographical / Historical
    This location is now part of Commodore Barry Park.
    Fort Greene (New York, N.Y.); New York Naval Shipyard
  - Coney Island Concourse Lands, V1974.3.38-42 (Box 1)
    Coney Island (New York, N.Y.)
  - Cooper Gore Park, V1974.3.43-44 (Box 1)
    Williamsburg (New York, N.Y.)
  - Cooper Park, V1974.3.45 (Box 1)
  - Cuyler Gore, V1974.3.46 (Box 1)
  - Dreamland Parking Square, V1974.3.47-49 (Box 1)
    This location is now the New York Aquarium.
  - Dyker Beach Park, V1974.3.50-56 (Box 1)
    Dyker Heights (New York, N.Y.); Bath Beach (New York, N.Y.); Fort Hamilton (New York, N.Y.)
  - Eastern Parkway, V1974.3.57-58 (Box 1)
  - Eastern Parkway Extension, V1974.3.59-60 (Box 1)
    Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Bushwick (New York, N.Y.)
  - Fidelity Memorial Park, V1974.3.61-62 (Box 1)
    This location is now part of the Brooklyn Queens Expressway.
  - Fort Greene Park and Playground, V1974.3.63-66 (Box 1)
  - Fort Hamilton Memorial Park, V1974.3.67 (Box 1)
    Fort Hamilton (New York, N.Y.); Bay Ridge (New York, N.Y)
  - Fort Hamilton Parkway, V1974.3.68 (Box 1)
  - Fort Hamilton Park, V1974.3.69-70 (Box 1)
  - Fort Sterling Park, V1974.3.71-72 (Box 1)
    No longer extant.
  - Freedom Square Park, V1974.3.73-74 (Box 1)
  - Fulton Park, V1974.3.75-76 (Box 1)
    Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.)
  - Grand Army Plaza, V1974.3.77-79 (Box 1)
    Park Slope (New York, N.Y.); Prospect Heights (New York, N.Y.)
  - Grant Square-Gore Park, V1974.3.80 (Box 1)
  - Gravesend Park, V1974.3.81 (Box 1)
    Borough Park (New York, N.Y.)
  - Greenpoint Park, V1974.3.82-86 (Box 1)
  - Greenpoint Park addition, V1974.3.87 (Box 1)
  - Joseph A. Guider Park, V1974.3.88-89 (Box 1)
    Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.)
  - Heisser Square, V1974.3.90-91 (Box 1)
  - Highland Boulevard, V1974.3.92-95 (Box 1)
    Cypress Hills (New York, N.Y.)
  - Highland Park, V1974.3.96-101 (Box 1)
  - Institute Park, V1974.3.102 (Box 1)
    Historical note
    This location is now the Brooklyn Botanic Garden.
  - Irving Square Park, V1974.3.103-104 (Box 1)
  - Jeannie Scott Dike Playground, V1974.3.105-106 (Box 1)
    Cobble Hill (New York, N.Y.)
  - William E. Kelly Memorial Park and Playground, V1974.3.107 (Box 1)
    Homecrest (New York, N.Y.); Midwood (New York, N.Y.)
  - Lindsay Playground (Box 1)
  - Leif Ericson Square, V1974.3.109-111 (Box 1)
  - Lincoln Road, V1974.3.112-113 (Box 1)
    Prospect Lefferts Gardens (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
  - Lincoln Terrace Park, V1974.3.114-116 (Box 1)
  - Linton Park, V1974.3.117-119 (Box 1)
    East New York (New York, N.Y.)
  - Marine Park, V1974.3.120-123 (Box 1)
    Gerritsen Beach (New York, N.Y.); Mill Basin (New York, N.Y.)
  - McCarren Park, V1974.3.124-126 (Box 1)
  - McKibbin Playground, V1974.3.127 (Box 1)
  - McKinley Park, V1974.3.128-131 (Box 1)
  - McLoughlin Park, V1974.3.132 (Box 1)
  - Memorial Gore, V1974.3.133 (Box 1)
  - Milestone Park, V1974.3.134 (Box 1)
  - New Lots Playground, V1974.3.135 (Box 1)
  - Ocean Parkway, V1974.3.136-137 (Box 1)
  - Old Glory Lookout, V1974.3.138 (Box 1)
  - Parade Place, V1974.3.139 (Box 1)
    Flatbush (New York, N.Y.)
  - Prospect Park Parade Grounds, V1974.3.140-143 (Box 1)
    Flatbush (New York, N.Y.); Kensington (New York, N.Y.)
  - Park Circle, V1974.3.144-145 (Box 1)
    Windsor Terrace (New York, N.Y.); Kensington (New York, N.Y.)
  - Parkside Avenue, V1974.3.146-148 (Box 1)
  - Plaza Street, V1974.3.149-150 (Box 1)
  - Prospect Park, V1974.3.151-155 (Box 1)
  - Prospect Place, V1974.3.156-157 (Box 1)
  - Recreation Pier #1, V1974.3.158 (Box 1)
  - Recreation Pier #2, V1974.3.159 (Box 1)
  - Red Hook Park, V1974.3.160-162 (Box 1)
    Red Hook (New York, N.Y.)
  - Red Hook Playground, V1974.3.163-164 (Box 1)
  - Saratoga Square Park, V1974.3.165-167 (Box 1)
  - Seaside Park, V1974.3.168-170 (Box 1)
  - Seeley Street storage property, V1974.3.171 (Box 1)
    Windsor Terrace (New York, N.Y.)
  - Shore Road, V1974.3.172-174 (Box 1)
    Bay Ridge (New York, N.Y); Fort Hamilton (New York, N.Y.)
  - Shore Road Drive, V1974.3.175-176 (Box 1)
  - Shore Road Drive Park, V1974.3.177-178 (Box 1)
  - Shore Road Extension, V1974.3.179-180 (Box 1)
  - Shore Road Park, V1974.3.181-182 (Box 1)
  - Owl's Head Park, V1974.3.183 (Box 1)
  - Sunset Park, V1974.3.184-187 (Box 1)
    Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.)
  - Tompkins Park, V1974.3.188-189 (Box 1)
  - Underhill Gore Park, V1974.3.190 (Box 1)
    Prospect Heights (New York, N.Y.)
  - Unnamed Gore Park #1, V1974.3.191-192 (Box 1)
  - Unnamed Gore Park #2, V1974.3.193 (Box 1)
    This location is now Fulton Park.
  - Unnamed Gore Park #3, V1974.3.194 (Box 1)
  - Unnamed Playground #1, V1974.3.195 (Box 1)
  - Unnamed Playground #2, V1974.3.196-197 (Box 1)
  - Unnamed Playground #3, V1974.3.198 (Box 1)
    Gowanus (New York, N.Y.)
  - Unnamed Playground #4 (Box 1)
    Greenpoint (New York, N.Y.); Williamsburg (New York, N.Y.)
  - Unnamed Playground #5, V1974.3.199-201 (Box 1)
  - Unnamed Playground #6, V1974.3.202-203 (Box 1)
  - Unnamed Playground #7, V1974.3.204 (Box 1)
  - Unnamed Playground #8, V1974.3.205-206 (Box 1)
    Gravesend (New York, N.Y.); Bensonhurst (New York, N.Y.)
  - Unnamed Playground #9, V1974.3.207-208 (Box 1)
  - Unnamed Playground #10, V1974.3.209-210 (Box 1)
  - Unnamed Playground #11, V1974.3.211 (Box 1)
    New Lots (New York, N.Y.)
  - Unnamed Playground #12, V1974.3.212 (Box 1)
    Gravesend (New York, N.Y.)
  - Unnamed Playground #13, V1974.3.213 (Box 1)
  - Unnamed Playground #14, V1974.3.214 (Box 1)
  - Unnamed Playground #15, V1974.3.215-216 (Box 1)
    Brownsville (New York, N.Y.); East New York (New York, N.Y.)
  - Unnamed Playground #16, V1974.3.217-218 (Box 1)
    Carroll Gardens (New York, N.Y.); Red Hook (New York, N.Y.)
  - Unnamed Playground #17, V1974.3.219 (Box 1)
    Sheepshead Bay (New York, N.Y.)
  - Unnamed Playground #18, V1974.3.220 (Box 1)
  - Unnamed Playground #19, V1974.3.221-222 (Box 1)
  - Winthrop Park, V1974.3.223 (Box 1)
    This location is now McCormick Park.
  - Williamsburg Bridge Playground, V1974.3.224-225 (Box 1)
  - Williamsburg Bridge Plaza, V1974.3.226 (Box 1)
  - Wynn Circle, V1974.3.227 (Box 1)
  - Zion Park, V1974.3.228 (Box 1)
    Brownsville (New York, N.Y.); Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.)
  - Zindel Park, V1974.3.229 (Box 1)
  - Drier-Offerman Park, V1974.3.230-231 (Box 1)
- Queens and Staten Island (Box 2)
- Manhattan and the Bronx (Box 3)